So now let's do that in Isabelle. And let me just say, so in Isabelle, so let me just say what we're
going to do in Isabelle, okay? So we're going to perform the proof. And this time, instead of
guessing the lemmas, I'll show you how we can find the lemmas. So find lemmas that are in Isabelle's
library, which is basically what we load when we say imports main, okay? So now let's go to Isabelle.
Okay, so we start another theory file quickly. So we just call it, let's say here, subst,
import again main, and then save that. We'll just save it, okay? So that's the theorem we have,
that's the theory file. Okay, so now let's just start by laying down the theorem that we want. So
we want to prove that X plus Y times A plus B equals X times A plus Y times A plus
X times B plus Y times B, okay? And then I want, remember we want to, because remember that natural
numbers are overloaded, so plus and y, and so numbers and operations and numbers are all overloaded.
So here we have this goal, but we don't know what the type is, so we can, you can see the type by
hovering over the object, for example, that you want. So C hovering and then doing control,
and then you'll see it. Yeah, so here this is a free variable of type A, so it's a polymorphic
variable. We want to fix the type, so we can fix that by saying that one of those is a natural
number, and then Isabelle will figure out that everything else is a natural number from that.
So here we hover around it and press control, and then you see the natural number, okay?
So now we have the goal, and we want to prove, we want to do like the three steps that we did on the
blackboard, right? So the first step is to do left distributivity. So we want to find a lemma,
so let's just do that first. So we want to find a theorem that says,
that does the left distributivity, if you recall from the board, right? Let's just go back to
the board and see that. So we want that lemma that we used for step number one, which is
that x times a plus b equals x times a plus x times b. So we want to find something like that.
So how do you find theorems in question? So instead of assuming these lemmas and saying,
sorry, what we, I mean, we can, of course, just do that. We can just say,
add this crib and then say, okay, x times a plus b equals x times a plus x times b. You can say that
and sorry it. And then, of course, you need to fix the types. But since this lemma is proved that
I know that for sure, so I would just show you how to find theorems. So how do you find theorems
in Isabelle? The way we find theorems in Isabelle in a second, we do it like this. So you say find
theorems and then you write the pattern that you're looking for. So in our case, the pattern is
x times a plus b. So that can be written like that. You can write it, of course, like
like this with the quantifiers. So x times a plus b. So basically, you're writing theorems
the same way that you're looking for. And then here we found like a lot of matches.
So we want like, for example, distributive distribute left. So that's the theorem that
we're looking for. So we can just say theorem distribute left distributivity like that. And
yeah, we have that. So we want that theorem. So let's just do the first step of our proof.
So let's go back to the blackboard to just remind ourselves. So that step was, yeah, so
in order for us to do that proof, we just will do the first step that we did in the board there.
So that was copying the left hand side. So we say have one. And then I would just say have
one equals undefined, which is just to, undefined is a placeholder of the correct type, just to make
sure that copied things correctly. And then I would just say, I removed the type annotation over the x
because the x has its type already annotated up there. So and Isabelle knows that because we're in
the proof context of that theorem, then all of these constants are the same from the theorem
statement. So what's the first step? So in the first step, we said that this x plus y times a
plus b equals, again, x plus y times a plus x plus y times e. And that should be done by
substitution. So how do we do substitution? So we say apply, subs, and then the theorem. So in our
case, it's called the strip left, which we found as I showed you earlier, undefined left. Yeah.
So then we have, then we're left with a goal where the left hand side and the right hand side are
exactly the same. And then you can close those goals by, if you have, let me just go back to
the notebook and just write that as a note so we don't forget it. So Isabelle, let me just write
a few notes. So let's find theorems. We have that. Also, a goal of the form x equals x can be
proved using two dots. Okay. That's one way to do it. So I'll show you how to do that, Isabelle.
Or you can do it. So that's one way. Or you can do it with, so here we have that now. We don't
have any goals anymore in that. We just have the main goal of the theorem, but we don't have,
but we close this step. Or you can also do it with the backward reasoning. If you recall,
we can also do this apply rule. But what's the rule here? We need a theorem that says that
everything is equal to itself. That theorem is called Reffel. So then you have, so let me
just show you that theorem. So with theorem, Reffel, it says that anything is equal to itself.
Any term is equal to itself. So that's what we have there. So we can do it that way,
or we can just do it with the two dots, and that's what I will do. Then we can have two.
What's the second step? So the second step was taking the right-hand side of the first step
and applying right-distributivity. So I will just show you how to find that theorem as well.
I mean, it's basically the same, but I'll show you to repeat the procedure. So here,
instead of saying x, instead of doing it that way, we do it that way. And then we just find
left-distributivity, which will be called, or right-distributivity, sorry. So that's it.
It's the one. So we'll copy this name, and let's see what it says. So it says what we
expected to say, like what we had in the paper. But instead of copying the right-hand side,
what we can do is, okay, of course, we can just copy the right-hand side like this, and then
unfolding this here, this x times a and y times a, and then we say apply subs,
and then this strip, right? Okay. So again, we have the same thing, and then we have this way.
So you can do it that way, but or instead of copying and pasting
the right-hand side, you can also do, I'll show you this later, how to do a chain of equations,
but let me just finish the proof here. Then we do the third step, and this is how you'd expect
it to be. But I want you to note something here. So here, we're applying distributivity,
but note that we have to put these parentheses around the result of line distributivity. Why?
It's because when we write, let me just do that on the blackboard because it will be easier.
So in Isabelle, like another note here, if we write a plus b plus c, let's say,
that can read as follows. This reads as a plus b plus c, okay? And what we did up there is that
we basically replaced that c with something else with some more complicated term. And then
because the term is more complicated, the parentheses will appear, will be visible.
So let's go back to the visible. So here, as you can see, then we have the parentheses around that
because that is more complicated than that. I think it's not very
interesting, theoretically interesting, but it's just a way of, it has to do with the way things
are parsed in Isabelle. And so we won't describe much how this is, or why this is like that. So
we can just do the same thing. Supply, subst, distrib, write, okay? And then we have the same thing.
Okay, and then we do the, all right. So now we have that this is equal to that. We just want
to remove these parentheses, and then we would have like a chain of equations, but it's not really
just finished that last step. So what do we want here? We want to add associativity, right?
Because we want to remove these parentheses from there, and we want to move them in one step.
So instead of XA plus YA plus all parenthesized XB plus YB, now we want this parenthesis to be,
to go in one step. So we want to look for a theorem that says the following.
So we want to say, we want to see something that says, we want to find something that says
A plus B plus C equals A plus B plus, and that is called semi-ring normalization rules,
but there must be something simpler than that, because it's a simpler name. Let's just fix the
types, and then I hope that is fine, what we will know. So I think that, you know, well,
okay, let's just copy this one, but that probably should be just the opposite of associativity.
So if we do this the other way around like that, this should be associativity. So we want like add
associativity, but we want it in the other way around. We want, so we want, remember we have
something with parenthesis, and then we will want to translate it to something that doesn't have
the parenthesis. So what we can do is, so this is what we have at associativity,
then what we need to reverse it by using symmetric. So this would give us the opposite of the rule,
which is the right direction. So let me write, let me also write down symmetric on our notes.
So if lemma 1 is x equals y, then lemma 1 with symmetric is y equals x. Okay, so now we need to
apply that rule again. So we're going, we're going to copy the left-hand side from there,
second, sorry, the right-hand side from there. That should be our new left-hand side,
and we want to remove these parenthesis. So we can just say by apply subst and asoc symmetric,
we have a problem in the theorem, same in the thread, that's why it's red, because there is
an error. So we have that, then we have the same thing as usual. Okay, and now we have,
okay, so now what do we have? We have a chain of equalities that basically has, says what we want.
So we can, so how can we do that? Remember, I told you that you can, these substitutions,
you apply them to our goal, and then they keep changing it. So we can just apply these
substitutions one after the other to that, to the final goal, and then it will change it
in the following way. You can just say show thesis, and then you apply subst one,
and then you apply subst two, and then you apply subst three, and then you apply subst four. So these
are all the transformations of the goal that we want, and then we have the final goal like that,
but the idiomatic way is able to do that is the following. So if you want to have a chain of
equalities like that, where you do substitutions or more than substitutions, this is how you do it.
So you can just say, okay, this is the first step, but then the second step, instead of saying have
two, you say also have, you can call it two as well, but instead of copying the right-hand side,
you can do this, and then instead of copying the right-hand side here, you can also do this,
the same, you'll have to say also, and then here you can say also as well. So here we're,
instead of copying all of these right-hand sides, we're just evolving our
chain of equalities, and now we can say finally, we can say finally have thesis, I guess,
thesis, which is the goal that we wanted, and then that's exactly what we have, because when you
do a chain of equalities like that, and then say finally in the end, what you have is an equality
between that, the first left-hand side, and the second, and the last right-hand side.
So you can, you can say finally have thesis by thought, because you already, because as I said
earlier, when if you have something, if you, if you have something, if you have, let me just
write two notes here, right? So two extra notes on Isabelle, first one is on if the goal,
I'll just call this Isabelle notes, if the goal is p implies p, so you want to show p and then you have
some p in your assumption, then you close it by adult, right? And the second thing is you can use
for representing a chain of equalities, you can say x equals let's say y, which is equal to z,
which is equal to a, which is equal to b, and then say, and then after you show all of these things
by substitutions or other means, you can say finally x equals b, and then you would have,
you'd have that, so you'd say have, and also have that, and also have that,
and also have that, and then you would have finally had this. So this is also an
a geometric way to do. So anyway, let's go back and finish this proof. So, so you say finally have
thesis. So thesis here is just, is a variable that basically has that expression in it,
stored in it. So, so you can say finally have thesis, or finally, I think show thesis. Yeah,
and that's it. So then we were done with that proof. And that's basically one proof by
substitution. So I think that's all for substitution. Thank you for listening,
and I hope you try it on your own and do it well.